Let's return to Kari on Garjin.   Are
you ready,
guys?  I
asked for artificial intelligence.  The guy
in the dark.  Yes.
[music]
And artificial intelligence, and I call
it artificial idiot.  Everything is mixed up.
mixes my ideas together.
Anyway, Dagarjina says, "Ah, well, that's it
, you've done your job, you've criticized
me. And about emptiness and why
emptiness means
that there can't be four higher truths and
so
on? You, yes, he said, "Yes, I told you everything
, don't wake up." And Arya Nagarjina
says to him, "And if you think that
emptiness means all these things, then it
means you haven't understood the goal, and it means you haven't
understood the essence, it means you haven't understood,
and you haven't understood the goal of emptiness, you haven't understood the
essence of emptiness and, uh, all the details of
emptiness."
And then and in the remaining chapter he
explains all these things. And I think you're
sitting
here.
And I want to hear from you tomorrow your
opinion about what this tre is.
When Nagarjina says, "You don't
understand the goal of
emptiness, you don't understand the
essence and the
details.  Maybe I think that you, what do you
think about this?
Oh, and we don’t have any comments
from
Arinagarjin here.
Chandrakirti wrote 400, 500 years later,
then we had Jenson Capa, but we don’t
really know what he meant.
Oh, and I’m wondering what you think about
this. Maybe you’ll cook in
your retreat cabins today. That’s exactly what
they’re meant for, yes,
to cook here and here. So,
cook this in your
retreat. And let’s talk about this
tomorrow. Do we have classes? No. Tomorrow,
on Tuesday.
So, tomorrow we have two classes, two
classes on translation.
Sometimes
the organizers, when they, when I give a
student, say: “Can you move
the classes?” I say: “No, they are
now part of all the
programs.”
So yes, I always say: “Let’s
translate your program.” That is, these
classes are now part of all the
programs.
Let’s move on to the
next one.
Actually, my deepest questions for me  they
come and in the bathroom. I'm trying
to work, and they, I can't go anywhere.
I'm getting questions everywhere. That's
why I got this question in the
men's
room. If you're the kind of person
asking questions, here's your
answer now.
They
say,
this is saying, when
there are
realities, they use a reality
that is
absolute and will need two
realities. You can't say that,
uh, fornication spends all its time in the void.
That's not true. They also
need a normal
reality. They use both absolute
reality and the regular standard
reality. And we have to
balance them.
I have some translation in the channel.
We have another translator in the channel,
guys. Everything disappeared. I think Ariana
Gargina is answering, uh, commenting on
this particular verse. This verse is number
eight, uh, from chapter twenty-four.
And he says, "Look, you need both
this and that
reality." I think we've seen,
uh, we've seen these, uh, extremes,  who are
simply used, who take advantage of
normal reality. They just
make money, they just
take care of their family, their children,
work. And that's all they do.
And they fail, because it's not
permanent. Children grow up or children
die, work also fails, the
business collapses, goes bankrupt. And the
hardest thing is, you have achieved success, and
then you just die. That is, there is no
future in all these things. And they
fail us, they lead to problems. And
they must lead to problems,
because this is the nature of ordinary
reality. But on the other hand, we
do retreats, we study
emptiness, we study the classics, we sit, uh,
visit one of our five houses. And
Nagarjina says that you
cannot do the second without the first.
Do you understand? You must have an ordinary
normal life. Then you can
make this life amazing, but you
cannot make your life amazing.
I live this life. It's great. In
fact, I had students,
I had a
teacher who was a student, and not only did I
suffer with my students, I also
suffered with his students for 25 years. And I saw
different
students. There was one guy, he heard about
renunciation, about lamrim. And he
said, he came to the teacher and said:
"I will live like a merciless person." And the teacher
said:
"True, yes." He says: "That's it, enough of
this
work."  I'll just live like Melorepa, I'll
be free, like Milorepa."
And the teacher said to him
: "And this guy, we lived in
New Jersey, we lived in a small
town, and there was this small forest
next to this
town." He says: "I'll live in the forest
, I'll go live in the forest." And the teacher
said: "You know, in New Jersey, actually,
there is autumn."
And it was just about to winter.
This is before global warming. It snowed a lot there
. It snowed really well.
He says to me: "No, okay, I'll still
stay in the forest." The teacher said:
"Okay." He says: "I'll give up all the
work, enough of this inconsistency.
Family,
that's it, I'm going to live in the forest." And the teacher is ready:
"Okay, let's see each other for now." And two weeks
later he came running back,
sits down in the kitchen and ate everything that
was in
the refrigerator. He says: "In this
forest there are no refrigerators." Yeah,
you know, actually, yeah,
[music]
no. Refrigerators are earned
with money, with work,
ugada.
And you need both.
Nagarjina says that you need both
normal reality, ordinary reality, and you
need absolute reality. And
actually, they support each other. They
go hand in hand. And have a
good job, have a
stable income. Don't go crazy, don't
work 18 hours a
day. Every job in the Universe creates
something that people need. That's why you
actually get paid. And it helps
people. If you build houses, if you
make refrigerators, cars,
you help people. My
father, oh, I thought he was like this
such a tough capitalist, because
he was building up
neighborhoods, and I was always afraid to
introduce him to the teacher. And finally, they had to
meet each other.
I was embarrassed. My wife, by the way, knows
my
dad. She, she, when I was 16, she
came to visit us, spent
time with us. I was like, "I don't really want
them to meet." And finally, my
capitalist father meets my teacher, the
keeper of the
dharma. And they were sitting in the kitchen of this
Mongolian temple.
And my teacher looked at my dad and
said, "I heard you're a big
businessman." And he said, "Yeah, I heard
you build houses for people, huge
neighborhoods, thousands and thousands of houses." He
said, "Yeah, my god, what a cool
dharma." I was like, "What?" And he was like, "What an
incredible activity, dharma.
Can you imagine how many
families you give
houses to? You're such a father, I wish I could be like
you." I was like, "  "What?  What's going on here
anyway?" And after that, my father
said, "Before this, I thought you were going to
become a
Christian monk, but I think
you're in the right place, a
Christian priest."
In this verse, Ariargajina says that
we need both. And the
absolutely weighty argument
that he offers here is so
cool. He says, "When Buddha taught
you in
emptiness, wherever that was,
and at the peak of the heart, when he taught
you the
heart sutra, did he use
words?  Did he write anything down?  Did
people write down the heart sutra?
Yes, this is not absolute reality,
this is a deceptive reality, this is
normal reality.  Books,
teachings,
translations, programs,
and all this is ordinary, normal
reality.  We'll go there and eat
normal food, I hope.
By the way,
the sponsors are Dr.
Vo, the doctor's student.  When I met
him, he says: "Do you need something?"  I
say, "Yes, I need a cafeteria."  I
say, "How much will it cost?"  I'm
like, "Well, I don't know."  That is, when you
talk to a sponsor, you constantly
double the price, raise the rate.  I
said: "200,000, I needed 100,000."  And
he says, "Yes, everything is fine."  And we
built it.  And it cost us 1.2
million. And I went to
him.  And in any case, he covered all the
expenses.  If you took Dr.
Wu's class this week, by the way, you should
definitely check him out.  And we
owe him a lot.  Do you want a secret?
I had a
translator.  She was a
young woman who lived in
Guangzhou.  And she said, "I'll
translate."  And I started: "Oh, we need a
retreat center."  And she's like, "She's
crying."  And then the sponsor is like: "You
need money? You need
money? And I always took it with you later
.
So, you also need a company that you
build houses, so that
and thank them that they are not
dharma students. They can count, they
can build, they can
build a roof, yes. Therefore, a real
dharma student, of course, must be both
. And that's why Ariana Garjina
says: "You need both, you need an
organization, there
must be buildings, there must be books,
there must be money in order to
do dharma." And that's what he
talks about
in this verse. This business does not necessarily have to
be dirty, bad. Business
can be tantric. Ah, and we
talked about this
already. Um, business can be the diamond
path. Ah, if you do it with the
right state of mind, then it is an
incredible incredible
practice. You just need to have such a
state of mind. Therefore, these two, they
need each other. This is what
Nagarjina says to his  criticism. He
says,
"Look, you need what we call
deceptive reality.  That is,
normal reality, we need it in order to
study absolute
reality.  We need both.  They are together all the time
.  Who's there?  He says who came up with it
.  When Buddha teaches dharma, he
needs both realities.  And someone has to
pay, I don’t know, for the
air conditioners.   It's
clear?  You need both.  And it's really
cool what he's talking about.
Wait, what's your
next picture guys?  Yes.   Yes.
Nagarjina
says: "There needs to be a balance."  There needs to be a balance between
absolute reality and deceptive
reality.  M, what do you
call this?  Ah,
baby.  Ah, a
swing.  I don't know
why Why is it so hard to find a
picture of this swing?
And he says
that
if he says that words are
absolute, it is a deceptive reality,
it is not absolute
reality, they are the cause of the effect of the
word.  And he says, "Without words, we
cannot attain absolute reality. Without
absolute reality, we cannot
attain nirvana. Without emptiness, we cannot
attain nirvana.
And in
Tibetan, you cannot teach dharma without
words, without terms. But words do not
refer to absolute reality, they
refer to a false reality.
So you need a false
reality. You need a false
reality to get to the true
real thing.
But Nagarjina has a very, very famous
line where someone says to him,
'Listen, tell me, what do you
really believe?  What is your true
position?" He says, "I believe in
what farmers believe in." That's a very, very
famous
line of his.
And what do these people who
plant these trees believe in? I believe in it, and that's very much so
. I believe in what
farmers believe in. Farmers understand that we can't
get trees if we don't have the
seed. Understand? So he says what
they say, and I
confirm it. The next picture
is
a little strange. I
tried. I don't know, you have no idea.
True, I fiddled around for a very long time.
For half an hour I tried to negotiate with
artificial intelligence. I needed a
lady who takes this
jewel from the head of a
snake.
And it does what you tell it to do. I
tried, I don't know, 20 times, probably, and
this is the best
result. I don't know what the
red thing is from her eye. It's unclear. I
apologize.
I didn't bother to find out what that red
thing is. In
So, here's the next verse. It says,
"When people don't respect emptiness, when
they say, 'Emptiness is stupidity.'"   I do
n’t know, there is no meaning in this
emptiness.  How does it even help in your
life if you think that something has
emptiness?  It's not clear.  And when they
speak ill of
emptiness, they possess little
wisdom.  That is, this little
wisdom is
destroyed.  And then he gives an example
from ancient times.
If you
wanted to know, in ancient times they believed
that very poisonous snakes had a
red ruby ​​in the
forehead area.  And he said that people
who do not respect the idea of ​​emptiness and who
try to study emptiness and do not understand
it, are people who are looking for poisonous cobras
in order to take this jewel from their foreheads
.  And in the end,
they are bitten by cobras and
die.  Everything that Arianagarjina
says goes much deeper.  There is always a
deeper meaning.
And what does he mean?  That studying
emptiness is dangerous.  It's like a cobra.  And you
can take the void, you
can take this
void, you can pull out this
diamond.  By the way, why is the snake important to him
?
Because Nagarjuna his name means
king or king of beasts,
cobras, snakes.  I'm
sorry.
By the way, Nson,
who worked for 17 years in one
Asian country in order to bring Buddhism
to
China.
Ah, and then he, it turns out, first wanted to
kill him, and then gave him this tower.
This is how the legend goes.  He visited the
great library in South India.  I
think this is John Brady in a past
life.  It was also
L. And Xuanzan
visited
the tower, this library of Arinaga
Garjina.  Arinaga Garjina collected
books.
He was also like John Reidil in his time
.  And he said, he thought it was
very important to preserve books, and he spent a
very large part of his life
preserving the early sutras.
For example, the Heart Sutra and the
Diamond Cutter Sutra.  Later he
built a library and tried to preserve
books.  He
visited Xuanzan,
translated, brought home about a thousand books
and translated them.  And this is how Buddhism appeared in
China.  And each of you who
watched The Lord of the Rings, they know
that this dragon can.  They like all
these, ah,
shiny jewels.  things, gold,
everything that sparkles.  And when dragons
hear something
valuable, they see something of value, they
try to take it all, and then they
sit on top of it, guarding it so that no
one steals it or no one uses it.
This is what people do with money.
So, he heard that the dragons, the
dragons had some
scriptures that they took to their
world, and he learned how to talk to
them.  He became a master at communicating with
them.  The Master appoints
Arjun.  This is such an archer, a great
archer, rich as Vita.  Oh, and he
became a dragon master.  And
he collected several boloblomido, a,
rajeni paramita from these nagas.  And he
brought them back to this world.  And that's why he knows
how to communicate with poisonous snakes
in order to take away the most
precious thing that is in them.  He
did it.  It's clear?  When he talks about
it, you need to know all the
background.  He says, "Emptiness is
like this precious stone that's
on the forehead of a dragon or a snake. And
to get to it, it's
dangerous. And
[music] there's a
very high probability that you
might get bitten. And you have to think about
that. Why Gardchun?
Oh, yeah, basically. People who don't
know what they're doing when they go after
emptiness, when they go, they try
to teach emptiness from someone who doesn't understand
this emptiness. They say, 'Close
your eyes, and in Chinese it means everything:
black black black on rock and roll.'
Just close your eyes and don't think about anything
, and then you'll get bitten. Do you understand what that
means? If you try
to learn about emptiness from someone who doesn't
know about it, then you'll get bitten by this
emptiness. And what does that mean? That's how you
understand, uh, how will it be if emptiness
bites you? That is, you've spent your whole life
sitting in  in a monastery and
stare at the wall and
think of nothing else. You've spent your whole life
trying to free and empty your
mind. And then
you got this poison. And it would have been better
if you worked at a gas station than to
sit and just stare at the wall and
think about nothing. This is a
complete waste of life and
time. At least they'll pay you
for this at the
gas station. And he
says, he gives another sign. You
can read
darani mantras in Sanskrit. And he says, people
who use darani, and they don't even
understand what they're doing, then
their darani
bites them, causing them
harm. Juanha was just talking about
this yesterday. If you're interested in the practices of Buddha
medicine, then for
God's sake, please read the report in
the book you received, which
explains how mantras work, otherwise the
mandras will bite you, and then
you'll waste your whole life, you'll just
die. And the people you're trying to
help with these mantras, and they'll get even
worse, or just  They won't work.
The worst thing is when, probably, it
seems to me that it doesn't work. Dying of
cancer is one thing. But when you read
mantras and die of cancer, that, I
think, is a very, very big
disappointment. Good. In any case,
Arina Gardzhina says: "You need
emptiness in order to understand mantras.
And you need emptiness."
And when you teach, study emptiness,
go into emptiness, then you must
do it with wisdom and
carefully.
And when you try to pluck out this
precious stone, and the eerie link,
then you need to conduct the right negotiations.
And he says that people who
study emptiness incorrectly,
they can imagine, right? That is, it
causes them
harm. I just have notes here, and
so now I will find what I need.
And what is your next picture,
guys? And what is the number of this
picture? Do you know?
Okay, I'll tell
you what number.
Wait.
6.11. And what was 6,10? What picture
was it?
Okay, yeah. And 11. Wait a minute.
Me. Okay.
Because I put together DCI courses. I
like to find modern pictures
that symbolize the ancient ones, and
resonate with the ancient ones, echo. And
here,
and here it symbolizes, and after
Buddha came  to sleep, he
doubted. He didn't want to teach for
7 weeks, he
doubted, and he refused. And that's what
this picture symbolizes. When you
see this picture, it's a professor
sitting in an empty classroom,
and he doesn't really want to teach.
Arianagarjina says in this chapter
: "Lord Buddha
realized that if he didn't teach
emptiness carefully, people would misunderstand it
."
And I say that in the last thousand years,
people have misinterpreted emptiness more
than they have understood it correctly. And you... I
hear all the
time, I hear things from different
people who say: "Emptiness
means clearing your mind, not thinking about anything
, nothing plays, nothing
matters.  You have to show kindness."
Well, everything is empty and so
on. Why do you think this
picture is connected to
this? Let me
repeat it again. Yes, it means that Ariana
Gargina recognizes that emptiness is a
difficult thing. And he says: "Why do you
think Buda sat there and
didn't say anything for seven weeks?  He
was afraid, he was afraid that they would not only not understand
, but that they would misunderstand.  And
so he thought it was better not to
talk about it at all.  And this is very, very
deep.  There is the greatest person
who explained emptiness in history, the
second Buddha Ariyana Garjina.  And he
says: “Why do you think the Buddha
hesitated to teach or not?
If it were not dangerous, but as if
it were so easy to
misunderstand, why do you think he thought about
it? And he
says: “But the holy heart of the Buddha, it
hesitated to teach this.”
He says: “The holy heart doubted
because he was afraid that people would
misunderstand.” Especially when we
say: “Yes, everything, everything is empty, and then there is no
need to be kind.  I can do whatever
I want, since everything is
empty." And he was very afraid of this, that
people would think this way. That's
why he refused
to teach. And he talks like this to
this guy. What does he say to this other
guy? Is it all your fault that Buddha
didn't teach or didn't speak for 7
weeks? True, true, in fact, it's your
fault. People like you are to blame.
And finally he decided
to criticize someone. Now, if I were to
choose one verse from the forty of this chapter,
which is called the study of what?
The four highest truths. If
I were to choose the most famous, the most
famous verse is this
next one. And my
Sanskrit teacher, he turns to
statistics, he loved statistics very much, and he
always kept notes like this,
how many times a word was mentioned in a book, and
he kept counting. This was
such a statistical approach to
studying the classics for him. And I was also brought up on this
. And when I wrote the
introduction to the
NNC books,  I liked to speak clearly. And I
would like to say what was the most
famous saying on Gargin,
which was used very often over the
past 2,000 years.
Top top 10, yes, the greatest hits of all
time. This is one of them. And you can
check. I sometimes do such strange
things. I did this in
Peru, Lima, in a
coffee shop. Who was there? With Stanley,
I think. And this is one of the most
famous things. It is in the top 10.
Everything is correct. For what? For what purpose is
emptiness correct? If emptiness
does not fit something, then nothing will
fit the definition of
emptiness. It's like
jeans. I will not explain. This is an
example that I use very, very
often. It's like a pair of jeans.
They either fit you, that is, and when
they don't fit, if they fit, then
there is emptiness, if not, then there is not. This is
very, very
famous. If it is empty, then everything is
fine. If it is not empty, then
Disaster. Nothing works without
emptiness. Don't think that emptiness
means nothing works. Emptiness
means everything works. If it's not
empty, it doesn't work. And let's
talk about
pens. Very simple
[music]
demonstration. 100% always true.
If you don't think so, then I built a
million-dollar business by accident. And that,
by the way, is also possible, but unlikely.
So, what is the dependent
origination of this pen? What does it
actually mean that all things depend on
something? What does that mean?
It actually means that they come from
seeds in your mind. That's
all. I've read all these
sociology books, I've read books on Buddhism, that
we're all connected,
blah blah. That's not what it's about.
Dependent origination. Simply
means everything comes from seeds in
your mind. Very simple. And it
comes from how you treated
people in the past. Everything comes from
how you treated people in the past.
Everything. Zero point is dependent
origination.  And don't worry about
anything anymore. Did
this pen come
from a factory in Japan or did it
come from the mind from the seeds of
Veshe? Well, by the way, a factory also
came from seeds, but in any case,
it is dependent origination.
What is it? What is the emptiness of a pen worth
$1,000?
And you can't
raise your hand until I ask a
question. Okay,
there is money for
$1,000. What is the best
way to teach emptiness to a crowd of
people? Okay.
Show them, while you show them, point your
finger for the rest of your life. If
you want to teach
emptiness, everyone raise your left
hand, index finger. This
finger. Don't use another finger,
especially in Arizona.
Point your finger at one of any one
thing in this room that does not
come from your
seeds. You need to add drama.
You need to
find some such one
thing. And then don't forget that
you also need
to point at yourself. That is, you need to add a little
drama. You can't just do it like that
. Then  This is what
emptiness is. That's all. This is the perfect
training in emptiness.
Perfect. You understand,
right? Then why do you get upset
when your husband yells at
you [music]? It's such a joke, right? Because
the old man forgot about the joke they taught.
We just finished
this topic at Diamond Mountain. I don't know, maybe 10 years
ago. By the way, there are
no people here who were in that group
. And one
person, well, he was a newbie. And after just
this lesson about emptiness,
oh, he says, he complains all the time,
complains all the time about Damontin.
And they complained all the time. He complained all the time
, complained. We
talk. And he keeps saying: "I'm
surrounded by idiots." And we
stand around him like that
. And we
[music] are
like:
"I see, this means that we, too,
all these idiots come from you."
Understand? And this is the best
postota.
If things  If things are empty, then everything works. If
things don't have emptiness, then nothing
works. And he
says the opposite, the opposite, at the
very beginning of the chapter. And he talks about
these four truths. The first teaching of
the Buddha. He says that emptiness
cancels out all four truths. And we
say: "No, if the
four truths have emptiness, they
work.  If they don't have emptiness, then
they don't work.  And this verse is one of the
most famous.  Sometimes you have to
memorize if you want to learn
Sanskrit, there is no simpler and more
meaningful
phrase in Sanskrit.  It is in this very
book that this verse is found.  By the way, I am using
the commentary of Choni Lama Drak Shedru,
who lived 300 years ago.
Oh, I hope I'll translate it someday
if people don't
distract me.  Okay, it's
612 now. We'll do a question and
answer session, I don't know, in 12 minutes.  Yes,
good.  OK.
Next.
Next.  And
it seems to me, yes, this is the eighteenth
verse.  By the way, if you've done
statistical analysis, this is also a
popular chapter.  The last
2000, like this hit song.
By the way, if anyone asks, ask,
what is madiamics?  The middle way, that's
your
answer.  Who better than Nagarjina can
explain to us what the middle
path is?  This is a very, very famous verse
when Aryangarjina explains what the
middle essence is.
He
says something we call
dependent origination.  That is, everything
that happens comes from the seeds in your mind.
When I say dependent origination, I
hate that
word, it means that all things
originate from seeds in your consciousness, in
your mind.  The way you treated people
in the past.  This is dependent
origination.  And this is emptiness.
Who said?
on
Gargin.  He says: "This is emptiness."
Is it technically a void?
No.  Emptiness is a negative thing, a
negative thing, and dependent
origination is a
positive thing.  Things work, right?  They
come from seeds.  Things don't work
because they don't come from seeds in
your mind.  Emptiness is always the
absence of something.
And dependent origination is something
that is there.  Therefore they cannot be the same
.  Technically, logically
they cannot be the same.  One
is absence, the other is
presence, availability.  So they
can mean the same thing.  Then he
says, "You want to know
what dependent origination is?"  So
emptiness is the fact that
we put labels on things.   A
shortcut is an expression of the middle way.
This is a pen, right?  And we put pens on her
label, right?  Is that why
we call it a pen?
No.  And a label usually means a name, a
title, which, uh, as if we were
hanging a price tag on some thing, uh, or
on bread, for example.  This is not what
this middle way means.  This means
that the label is placed by your mind.  And this
labeling happens all the time
with the help of mental pictures.  The seed
opens in your mind and a mental
picture pops out and it covers
that
thing.  Yes, remember, and two, I always
give this image.  Two delicious ginlatu
Italian ice cream.
And then you say, "Pour some
chocolate
sauce over it and some really strong coffee to
top it all off."  And here is this
picture, when the chocolate glaze
covers this, and the ice cream, in
particular, covers this stick, and
it turns into a pen.  When we
say pictures, when we say
labels, it means putting labels on things
using pictures.  And that’s why the dog
looks, can look and say:
“I don’t want to live with her.”  By the way,
everything is simple with a dog.  It seems that it sounds
too simple and it seems that cheap
simplifies everything.  No, I'm not simplifying it.  If
the dog sees something else, if the dog
wants to live this way instead of
writing a poem with this thing, it
proves the emptiness of the pen.  And you don't need
2,000 years of classical house to understand
this.  Seriously?  Seriously.  If a dog
sees something
different, it proves that it has
simplicity.  That's all.  And it's very
simple.
And no one in the Universe can argue:
“No, the dog sees it as a pen,
it just forgot about
it.”  You can't say that.  If
the dog actually sees something
else, you can prove that she is chewing
it, she is not writing, then she must be
seeing something else.  And this proves
that this thing is empty.  That's all.  You
don't need anything else.
The fact that the dog does not see the pen is
proof of Buddhism.  This is
proof that Buddhism is right.  And
this is proof that you cannot
die if you understand emptiness, if you
understand Buddhism.  So this thing, the
dog, is the truth, it’s
proof.  And there was this guy in
Florida who tried to prove me
wrong.  Most likely he was in Florida.   I
don't
know, something happened there recently.
Okay, I won't say anything
bad.  And the fact that
the pen comes from your
seeds, what will be the
final line here, the conclusion, the
outcome.  This is the middle way.  Don't
tell me what madiamics is.
By the way, both.  Madiamika,
madiamaka.  Don't ask me what the
middle way is.  This is the
middle
way.  Things are between dependent
passage and emptiness.  This is the
middle way, and this is the highest school of
Buddhism.  There is nothing higher than this.  And this is
also Buddhism, which is used in
Tantra.  The Diamond Path, it depends on the
diamond.  The Diamond Way is the
Madamika school.  Fine.
Well, we still have 4
minutes for Gardzhiny.
Fine.  Oh, and now this, these
great
Buddhist thinkers, they do cool
things too.  They probably play Jamie
Hendrix too.  We played.
Next
verse.  Why are they? Why is it
cool?  I will not offer money.  Just
say it, you can
shout.  Yes.
He says that he uses his
opponent's logic against him.  And that's
just his style.  He always
ends up like this.  And as a wife and
husband, listen, by the way, he
uses the same Sanskrit words as
his opponent used at the very beginning.
He comes back and says, "You know what,
dear?
If things are not empty,
then the truths, the four truths, are wrong.
Because the other one, remember how he started
the chapter? He says, "If things are empty,
then the four truths are wrong." She
Gargina says, "So you know
what?  When I think about it, if things aren't
empty, then the four truths
are wrong." And the guy's like, and he's
using the same words, he's
using the same language against
this
guy. But by this time he's already
explained about the mental seeds, and he's
talked about the pen. And he says, "You know
what?  When I think about it, if it's
as you say, then there are no
four higher truths." And by the way, I did
n't add this whole series of arguments to the lesson
. If there is no emptiness, then there are no
truths, then you can't
appeal to the results of these four
truths, and so on and so forth. He
repeats all this. Remember what we did?
If things are not empty, then you and I have a
problem. Okay. I think that's so
cool. And this is really, really powerful
.
Come on. Yeah, yeah. There will be a question and
answer session. Let's finish. Let's
[music]
finish, because we have the
original work to finish
this.
Okay. Next picture.
Plaster. Can you read Tibetan?
Tazi
And we printed. And we use, we
don't use Chinese, but Chinese
transliteration or Hebrew.
After we started the project in
1983, eighty-
seven, all the
computers they used
Roman, yes,  Latin alphabet, and that's why we
started using it too.
And one of the
weaknesses of the Xuanzan Tower is that
the translators couldn't read what was
engraved on the tablets. They're very
complex. And
the problem is that they got
confused back then, they tried to enter the letters so that the
engraving would work on a piece of
wood. That's why it was very difficult.
This optical recognition system, it
also makes mistakes, just like the
person who enters this
data. The same
result. And so you see what the
problem is. For zero dollars.
Gipson. Who is Pusiku? Pusaku. Pusaku
. Pusuku. Shantideva. Yes, that's
Master Shantideva. His nickname. And it
means
lazy, good-for-nothing.
And if you want to pay a compliment,
and say to your friend: "And you're like
Shantideva, you're just a busu."
Because the people at the monastery thought he was
lazy, good-for-nothing, but he was
very, very busy.  uh, when he wrote at home
and didn't do it in
public. And he wrote one of the greatest
books, uh, that was ever
written. And I'm
very there three three three courses tenth,
eleventh, twelfth, right? That is, I
doubted whether to remove them from these courses or
not,
but so, Basuku is the
master of the activity of Bathhisattva, and no one
wrote a greater book on the
way of life of the
satov than Busuku, than Shantedeva.
By the way, in the ancients, as they call him,
they are proud of him, even on the contrary.
Oh, you call him lintyam? Dada.
Call him
litaya. Everything, everything he did everything secretly, it's all about
secrecy, he never
put his work on display. And Arinagarjina
says: "If things, and if things are the way
you want them to be,
if things are not empty, then there is no Buddha, and
then there is no bahisatchariya."
Yes, he says that there are no matkisa.
According to
to you, he's actually now attacking
this guy, the opponent. He says, "Yeah,
yeah, you're right.  There are no truths if
things are not
empty." By the way, there are no three
precious things that are not empty. And there is
no Buddha if things are not empty. And you
cannot become a Buddha because there are no
six perfections. According to you.
I see. At this moment, in this moment, Yes. At
this moment, Ariana Gargina is already
criticizing him openly. According to you,
we don’t need the six perfections.
Shantideva just, maybe he really would have been a [ __ ]
, he wasted his time. I see.
And now, when you see this
picture, by the way, you will remember that without
emptiness there are no bathisat. Forget
about the three jewels, forget about
bathisat. No one can become
a bathisattva. You cannot practice
Buddhism, the six perfections, if you don’t
understand emptiness. And it is emptiness
that makes them perfections.
And, by the way, this is the last question session we will do with
you
. New books are coming out: Rose
from Rose Vangrikin. You  should
say:
"Hurray!" She does two cool things. She is
in charge of everything and the entire editorial staff of the entire
publishing house of translations mixnat. We have already published 14
or 15 books
. No one has done this in the
last,
what? 1400 years. No one has done what
we have been doing in the last 600 years. It's
great, it's incredible. And in many ways, we are
grateful to Rosa. If you see her,
thank her, she works very hard
. And she does two cool
things. My early books I did with a big
publishing house in New York, and they
had the rights. I can't, but she negotiated with them
, and now we have the rights,
and to print a certain
number of my old books.
And they don't want to give us all these
rights. Anyway, she negotiated with them
. And now this is in honor of the
twenty-fifth anniversary. 25 years have passed since
I
wrote the garden. And it's about an amazing
angel. And it
's 30 years since I
translated the main teaching of Buddhism, Yoga
Sudra. Oh, so we have permission from
this publisher. Oh, and now you
can also order these books. Here
you go. You know what this is?
And then we also released a hardcover
edition of Meditation on Emptiness, which
fell short. The Betgrer translation is
the best book on meditation on
emptiness. And it will contain all
the details of all the meditation techniques. Even
if you don't want to read about emptiness, the
second part is about how to meditate. And
these are Kamalashila's instructions on how to
meditate. In any case, these books
are available. I'm not
advertising now, I'm simply talking about what
Nagarchuna says at the very, very
end. By the way, we finished the
chapter, and he
says: "If you truly
understand emptiness, then you understand
semena."  If you are a master of emptiness, you
understand the seeds."
And from this
statement a
very famous genre
of literature emerged, when people sang, chanted
love songs, praised Buddha because
he taught for so long
. You are so beautiful, you are so
wonderful, you taught us emptiness. And he
taught emptiness through seeds. That is, and this whole
theme of these balatas, songs, and there is a whole
collection of these
songs that are dedicated to Buddha and where they
praise. Oh, you are so beautiful,
because you taught in emptiness through seeds. The
most important thing here is through seeds. And
the coolest song, a beautiful song
is called Tenderropa.
Praise to
Buddha. Praise to Buddha for teaching
emptiness in the form of seeds or through seeds.
And
you will finish the translation of this commentary tomorrow. Gibson
is finishing this translation tomorrow, so
you can be present at this
translation.
He literally has a couple of
sentences left. We slowed down so much on
purpose, because it's like asking your husband to go to the
toilet.
wash. He's in no hurry to do it. But
I think we'll finish tomorrow. Or we'll
prolong
the pleasure, I guess.
That's where this verse comes from, the
last verse. This chapter. It's when
Nagarjina says: "Listen, there's
nothing more attractive than
dependent
origination that attacks, hacks the
void." If you really
understand, then you understand that this is a
couple, they're a sweet couple, right? And he
talks about it.
Yes. Yes. I think we'll stop here. So
, any questions? Then, so you don't
complain that I'm not answering your
questions. Guys, you
take care of the microphone. Thank you for teaching,
thank you for coming. Glad to
see you. It seems to me that it was there when it
began 100 years
ago. I was thinking about the truth.
The truth, especially the laws of
karma, which is very close, and is
subject to the laws of karma, and some kind of
self-existing question. What's
happening in the world today, how to think about the
truth of the laws
karma
or
how to connect this with
what is the truth of people?
As any jihadist
would say, jihad said that this is the
closest, fastest way to get to
heaven. How to think about truth in our
modern world and understand what the
truth is? I will say what I think about
it. What would Buddhism say to this question
?
We call it the three standards of
gold. It took me a long time
to understand. And I kept coming back
to them again and again and again. In ancient
times, when you bought a horse, you
paid, I don’t know, in grain, for example, you
said, you traded 100 sacks, 300
sacks and so on.
Then there was no, as they call it in Chinese
, there was no, there were no payments of any kind
. Ah, there were none. There were no
credit cards. There were no
credit cards, there was no
cash, there were no gold coins. And
before there were no gold coins, there were none
. Not when you bought a
horse, you  They paid in corn or grain,
and you...
Oh, by the way, the old way, and how to burn
money, and that means
burning... I believe in Bud more than in the
supermarket.
I will burn money in order to
offer it to Bud, and
then I won't be
able to. I believe in Bud so much that I will
burn all the money, offering it
to him. That's what the fire offering ceremony is
. And people started
using gold.
And dishonest people, they started to cover
it all with different other metals.
Or there, for example, with lead, yes, and there
was just a little bit of gold. And
these three tests of gold appeared. Kche,
yes. And burn it or melt it or saw it
, chop it, cut and
file it. How do you know the truth? These are the three
tests of gold, traditions.
And this is in the days when they bought
horses. Sek
means when we decide what is true
or not, one part. Can we
confirm this with our direct
experience? It's difficult when we talk about
jihad.  Have you ever killed, killed an
infidel, and then gone to heaven? I do
n't know. I haven't gotten there yet.
You see, this is direct experience in this
case, probably not. It's probably
impractical. And there's a second test of gold,
which is called a check. This is when we
cut it and look
inside, with a special instrument.
And this applies when we
confirm something with
logic.
And this is when Buddhists would answer. But
initially, they say that there is a
sequence between, and
cause and effect. You sow a pumpkin,
you will get a pumpkin. If you sow
violence, you cannot get
happiness. All this other stuff is
illogical. Forget about all
religions. How you were raised is unclear.
You,
uh, planted hot peppers and got a
banana tree. Therefore, it is illogical
to say that violence can lead to
happiness. And this is the second test. Atar
is a gift. This is when we saw into it.
This is
gold. We call everything
destructive tests.  Yes, we don't
break a diamond to see
the real thing. No, they don't use that in the diamond business
. And the third test of gold is that
you file it down to
find out if there are impurities of other
metals. Maybe it's an authority, yes, it's an
authoritative
source. With an authoritative source,
but until now, I followed this
advice on everything that is good.
Yes, here it's
a little weaker compared to logic
.
And all the things that he tried,
which he hung up, I tried and they
worked. And he didn't say that I can't
confirm that if I kill people, I
will get to nirvana.
Everything he told me in the past, I
tried, and it
worked. These are the three tests of
gold. If you find
a person you can
trust, that's why it takes so much
time to use in order to
find your spiritual teacher. You
have to check him, check,
check, check. And only then you
start following
him. This is how a Buddhist would answer. This
Three tests of truth. How do we test
truth? If this statement
passes all three of these tests, then we
say it's certainly, most likely,
true. So
it's
true that we're going to have breakfast now,
right?
Getting ready? Yes. So I'm telling you it's
true, so you go and check whether it's true
or not. Authoritative source.
Thank you. Ah.